Multi asset
allocation funds have outperformed major equity categories in the last one year due to the strong rally in gold and silver.
Among multi-asset funds,
ICICI Piden Multi-Asset Fund is
in a league of its own.  The AUM of this fund is
almost Rs 8800 crore.  The
second largest fund in the category, SBI Multi Asset
Allocation Fund, has an AUM of around Rs 15,000 crore.  The
combined AUM of the next 10 funds in the category will
equal the AUM of ICICI Piden Multi Asset Fund.   The
AUM of this fund has grown at a rate of 33% per annum in the last 7 years.
This number tells everything
about the popularity and performance of this fund.
So naturally, such a
big fund should be observed to see
how it is being managed and
what is the reason behind its success.
Hello and welcome to ETy Hindi.  Today we
will analyze ICICI PDL Multi Asset Fund.
By mandate, multi asset allocation funds are required to
invest in at least three asset classes
and
maintain a minimum allocation of 10% in each asset class.  So multi
asset allocation funds mainly
invest in equity and gold.  In this video,
we will look at how ICICI Piden Multi Asset
Fund has historically invested in these assets
and on that basis, we will
try to decode the strategy of this fund.
So let us start with the
performance details of ICICI Piden Multi Asset Fund.
To understand the performance of this fund in perspective, it is important to first know a little about its history.
So ICICI Principal Multi
Asset Fund was launched in October 2002.   At that
time its name was ICICI Piden Dynamic
Plan.  Then it was an equity fund which could
invest anywhere and in any proportion.
It could have invested its entire corpus in equities
or
shifted completely to debt depending on market valuations.
This was a very aggressive mandate.
In 2011, three more ICICI Prudential funds
namely ICICI Prudential Fuse Fund, ICICI
Prudential Equity Opportunities Fund and
ICICI Prudential Fuse Fund Series III were
merged into this fund.  Then in May 2018, after SEBI's
changes in mutual fund categories,
it was reclassified and made a multi-asset fund
and the name was also changed accordingly.
So basically its mandate
expanded from an equity fund to a multi asset fund.
That is why only fund data after May 2018
is useful for us.  This fund has seven
fund managers and the most senior among them
is Sankaran Narendra who has been leading this fund since February 2012.
So now, keeping
in mind the background of this fund, let us
compare its rolling returns with its peers.
Most of the funds in the multi-asset category are quite new.   Out of
34 funds, only eight funds have a
history of 5 years.  This is the reason why
a large part of the total money of this category is
with ICICI Prudential Multi Asset Fund.
Because very few funds have long
term data.  So to compare the performance
we will
use average three years rolling returns from January 1st, 2019.  The 3-
year period is neither so short that it
appears unreliable nor so long that
most of the funds get filtered out.  For 3-year
rolling returns, we calculated
every possible three-year
return from January 1, 2019, and then averaged them all.
But
why are we taking rolling returns?  Because rolling
returns are
based on data from a large number of trailing returns.  That's why it
gives a much more reliable picture than simple trailing returns.  OK, now
you see the chart on your screen.
ICICI PDL Multi
Asset Fund comes in second with an annual return of around 27%.  This
is a good performance.  But this is only
half the picture.  Returns should always be
compared with their underlying volatility.
To measure volatility, we will
use a metric called
standard deviation.  Now
the higher the standard deviation, the higher the volatility.
So in terms of volatility, ICICI Piden
Multi Asset Fund comes at the third last position.
This means that this fund has
delivered high returns amid high volatility.
If we compare the returns and volatility of this fund
with Nifty 500 TRI, then
this fund has been slightly more
volatile.  But the returns have also been incredibly
rewarding.  Therefore this
volatility does not hurt investors.
Because
this fund does a better job of containing the downside compared to Nifty 500 TRI.
Nifty 500
TRI has given negative returns in nine quarters since January 2019 and
ICICI Pidensal Multi
Asset Fund has done better in eight of those nine.  This is very strong
down side protection.  Many times,
this fund has delivered positive quarters even when the market fell.
So
this fund scores high from the perspective of both overall returns and volatility.
Now we will look at how this fund has
invested historically.  But before that,
if you have not yet subscribed to our channel, then do
subscribe
so that you get notifications of every upcoming video.   If we
look at the half-yearly asset allocation of ICICI Prudential Multi Asset Fund from January 2019 till date, the
equity allocation of the fund has been between 64% to
75%.  Debt allocation ranges from 7% to
15% and others include Gold,
Silver and Leads InvITs.  It has ranged from 16%
to 27%.
We will discuss the other portions of this fund in detail later.  For
now, let's compare this broad
allocation with the category.  From
which we have removed this fund and
checked this allocation.  The category's equity
allocation has ranged between 55% and 66%.  Debt
allocation between 12% to 21% and Others
allocation between 20% to 30%.  Clearly, this
fund
prefers to invest more in equity and
comparatively less in debt as compared to its category.  The fund's other
allocation is also slightly on the lower side.  So
with ICICI Pen Multi Asset Fund you
can expect an equity tilt.  And
this is the reason behind its high returns and high
volatility profile.  Now let us
zoom in further into the equity portion of the fund
and see what its market cap allocation is.
This fund prefers to be heavy in large caps.
Large cap allocation has
ranged from 69% to 92%.  Mid caps have been between 3% and
19% and small caps between 4% and
11%.  We had also seen this thing in one of our earlier
videos.  When we talked
about two other funds managed by Shankar Naren.
If you want to know
how India's top fund managers are positioning their portfolios in today's market,
we have a dedicated video on that.
You will find the link in the description.
Ok.  So let's go back to the
market cap allocation of ICICI PDL Multi Asset Fund.
You will get to see an interesting thing.  The
fund's large
cap allocation has been continuously declining over the past few years.
By January 2026, it had reached its lowest level
i.e. 69% and consequently
mid and small caps were at their highest levels.
Mid caps were at 19% and small caps at 11%.
Now let's see what the category is like.  The
category's large cap allocation has ranged from 69% to
82%.  Mid cap allocation between 12%
to 18% and small cap allocation between 4% to
15%.  The same trend is visible at the category level also.
Large cap allocation is
falling.  Whereas allocation to mid and small caps
is increasing.  In terms of overall market cap
allocation, ICICI Prudential
Multi Asset Fund prefers large caps.
Rest of the funds and categories have
similar market cap allocation trends.  This inclination towards large caps is
understandable because the fund is
more invested in equities, so there are
large cap safer options to reduce risk.
Now let us talk about the
debt allocation of the fund and check the
yield to maturity i.e. YTM of the debt allocation of the fund.
If you are not familiar with YTM then let me
explain it briefly.
YTM means if you buy a bond at today's
price and hold it till maturity, then the
total annualized return you will get
is YTM.  It has three components.  The
bond's coupon payments, capital
gains or losses, and the assumption that all coupon
payments are reinvested at the same rate.
But why check YTM?  If the
YTM of a fund is higher than the category average,
it means that the fund is
taking more risk.  Either buying lower grade
bonds or longer duration
bonds or both.  Lower grade bonds carry the
risk of default and longer
duration bonds carry the
risk of rising interest rates.  Now if we talk about this fund,
its YTM has been between 4.35% to 7.23%.  On
the other hand, the category average has been
between 4.37 to 7.43%.  This means the
fund manages its day portfolio in line with the category average.
And
in relative terms, it does not take much risk to extract extra returns from the day.  If
we look at the credit rating breakdown of the day portion of the fund,
cash, sovereign and top rated day securities have a
major share in it.  On the duration side, the
average maturity of the fund is currently above 5 years.
But most of the time it has remained around 2 years.
Which shows that the fund
prefers shorter duration bonds.  This
means that the
fund is currently quite conservative in taking duration risk.  Yes, the
average maturity has increased in the last 6 months.
Perhaps because the fund is positioning for a lower interest rate
environment and
locking in long duration bonds.
Now we will see what is the strategy of the fund in other asset
allocation like Gold, Silver, REITs, InvITs.
Now, splitting the remaining asset allocation was a
big challenge.  This data
is not directly available anywhere.  So, for this
we checked the old fact sheets of ICICI Piden Multi Asset Fund
and extracted
all the data from their portfolio disclosure.
To compare this, we
also collected data of the next three largest funds by AUM, which include
multi asset allocation funds of SBI, UTI and HDFC.
For this we had to
look at a lot of fact sheets.  That's why the data
you're about to see is quite unique and
you won't see it anywhere else.  Let us
first check the allocation of other assets of ICIC PDL Multi Asset Fund.
According to the data points we looked at, the fund's gold
allocation has ranged between 6% and 13%.
Gold allocation has been falling steadily since July 2022
and reached a low of 5.9% by July 2025.
But in January 2026, it
bounced back and reached above 9%.
Silver also entered the fund's portfolio during this period.  In January 2025,
this fund had an exposure of 4.17% to silver.
But by January 2026, the
fund had zero allocation to silver.
If we compare gold and silver prices from July 2022 to January 2026,
silver has outperformed gold by a huge margin.
While silver has
given almost five times returns in this period,
gold has generated three times returns.
This means that the fund's silver
allocation has worked tremendously in the fund's favor.
Now that silver has started falling,
this fund has safely exited silver.
Silver has corrected by more than 22% in the last one month itself.
This clearly
shows that the fund has taken a very smart
technical call on silver.  Apart from gold and silver,
this fund also invests in REITs and InvITs.
Now the question is how does the other
asset allocation of this fund compare to its three major
competitors SBI, UTI and HDFC Multi
Asset Fund?  These funds
mostly focus on gold.  As
we have seen, their gold allocation has been between 8% to
16%.  According to our data points,
silver first entered their aggregate portfolio in July 2024
and it still remains a part of it.
But it is worth noting that
both HDFC and UTI do
not have any allocation to silver.
Silver is visible only in SBI's portfolio.  This
means that SBI Multi Asset Allocation
Fund has also made profits from the silver rally.
But it entered quite late as per ICICI PDL Multi Asset Fund.   On
the other hand, if we talk about REITs and IMITs,
their share in the aggregate portfolio is
higher than that of ICICI Piden Multi Asset Fund.
These calls from these funds were quite beneficial
as REITs and InvITs have performed very well in the last one year.
And this is something that ICICI Pensal
Multi Asset Fund needs to pay some attention to.
Now, if you look at the overall allocation of ICICI
Multi Asset Fund and its peers across other
asset classes, you will see it on your screen.
Let's quickly summarize all the findings of this video
in the concluding section.
With an AUM of over Rs 80,000 crore,
ICICI PDL Multi Asset Fund
is the true titan in this category.  This fund alone
commands 42% AUM of the entire category.
This fund has also been an outperformer in terms of returns.
It has also outperformed the pure equity Nifty 500 TTRI.
But this
performance has
come with slightly higher volatility than its peers.  However,
volatility does not necessarily mean a
large drawdown.  The fund has
also managed the downside quite well.  So there is nothing to
worry about on the overall performance front.
This outperformance is due to the
fund's overweight equity stance.  This means that
it has invested more money in equity than its peers.
Additionally, the fund
identified the silver opportunity ahead of time and made substantial profits from it.   The
fund's tactical strategy
is clearly visible from its silver bed and
looking at the latest portfolio, the fund has
now completely emptied its silver bucket.  Whereas
in equity allocation, the fund prefers large caps.
Perhaps this is a safety
measure as the fund's equity allocation remains
quite high.  The fund's debt
allocation is lower than its peers.
If we look at the yield to maturity, it
seems that the fund is not trying to take much risk on the day side.
Also, this
fund invests less in gold and reed InvITs as
compared to many funds
as its focus
is more towards equity and this is
not surprising as earlier this fund was an equity
fund.  The influence of its
senior most fund manager Sankaran Naren
is clearly visible on the strategy of this fund.  Overall, this fund remains a
favorite of investors for this reason.
So what do you think about this fund
?  Do tell us in the comments and
yes, don't forget to like and share this video.  That's all for
today.  We will
meet you soon with another insightful video.
Until then take care.
Mutual fund investments are
subject to market risks.  Read all
scheme related documents carefully.